so previously I was taught about bra
viharas and I want to come here and find
some clarity in regard to them and I
found a suit that speaks on them
it's called removing resentment and
that's how its translated you know and
good for nakiya one 6:161 mmm because
they're these five ways of removing is a
resentment by which a be gue should
entirely remove resentment when it has
arisen towards toward anyone what 5:1
should evoke love and kindness for the
person one resents in this way one
should remove the resentment toward that
person once you develop compassion and
and so once you develop equanimity or
one should regard the person one resents
had paid no attention to him in this way
I want you to remove that resentment or
one should apply the idea of ownership
of kama to the person one resents thus
this venerable one is the owner of his
comma the Arab has come he has come as
his origin relative resort he is the
heir has come up good or bad in this way
one should remove the resentment toward
that person these are the five ways in
which removing resentment by which
should be gue should entirely remove it
I was wondering that thought
it could be I guess more about in regard
to met compassion equanimity and ethics
translating is loving-kindness but it's
quite actually
silly translation keep your loving their
kind it means friendliness so like imagine if
it means friendliness so like imagine if
your friend is saying well imagine if a
stranger is saying something hurtful to
you would you think you get upset now
imagine if your friend start saying
something like you really really good
friend it's gonna be much harder to get
upset because you experience that person
through the framework of friendliness
they are your friend so that's the
difference it's not what they said and
how they said it and how you reacted
it's the context of that saying that's
basically it's something for your mind
is responsible for so you want to
practice matter as in you want to
develop the framework of friendliness
towards all beings all beings their
friends even the ones they want to harm
you you cannot possible experience your will
you cannot possible experience your will
a loving kindness it's more of like a
smarmy thing to do or but I love them
they they're hurt but I love you back no
that's you always shoot in the market
you don't need to love them you just
need to not hate them that's the down
part of us since hatred is not abandoned
by hatred by only by non hatred you can
abandon hatred and people often jump to
translate that by saying by love you
abandon hatred no you abandon love by
non love you've been hatred by non
hatred love is an equal impediment as
hatred is so think of meta is
friendliness that's why if you are a
friendly disposition you can't hate
anyone that's the natural compassion
already if you if you're if your
perspective is not restricted with your
anger and your conceit you already that
perspective in itself is what carries
compare because you have a better sight better
because you have a better sight better
again better perspective on what's going
on and that's why we also that then
common is really in equanimity
foreground movie house she friendly if
you're compassionate you've been
different whatever the person chooses to
do you will not prompt ale willing you
we will not from lust in you so you will
be economist as you know mm-hmm I guess
compassionately the opposite of
compassion is not cruelty I suppose not
the desire to yeah yeah compassion is a
translation yeah you can say it's a non
cruelty hmm so that would be the
difference between this friendliness and
compassion is friendliness is in the
lens of seeing whoever it is as a friend
and compassion in regard to any sort of
it's even more yeah more encompassing
them yeah it's even more encompassing
than just friendliness the families is
the basis and it's a sufficient basis I
mean you you can just develop Metta and
experience complete this passion
eventually as a result of that framework
and that's the that's the thing so if
you were to take it further the same
principle can you develop compassion he
would just be extended even further in a
sense of it's not even like it's not
just about the person but even whatever
they were to do you would still maintain
compassion as and you would still act
and make the effort if it comes to it
for their well-being as opposed to
acting it out of there yeah yeah you
wouldn't be acting in response to what
they're doing because you wouldn't lose
perspective because you are already
established upon the framework of
friendliness that's I mean the
compassion will naturally come out of it
mm-hmm because you're not compassionate
when you lose the greater picture you
know like that you ever been experienced
I don't know somebody said something and
you get angry Nozomi
these parents just died or something and
then suddenly feel compassionate
although nothing has really changed he's
still insulting and saying bad things to
you I don't know but now you don't angry
with him because you kind of understood
but like context that he's in pain
mm-hmm and then you can't have the anger
so you have anger when you don't have
perspective but now imagine you develop
the ultimate perspective that doesn't
even depend on the context in regard to
that person even if his parents didn't
die even he's not in the pain he's just
being another complete idiot ruled
whatever offensive he's still a being
and that's like that beings are over
owners of the commode of his all of they
come they don't like you it's not like
like something you need to psychologize
and how is the money he'll pay the price
no literally means recognizing that
knowledge that beings are bound with the
karma means for he subjected to his own
actions to his own lack of wisdom to his
own ignorance to his own passions
completely unaware of it and you cannot
be upset on that account because that's
what ignorant beings are so in that
sense you wouldn't have any animosity
virgin
have another shooter do it with the next
one following it also called moving
resentment mmm it says it goes through
five ways Oh before you go for next to
the that's why also that friendliness
you practiced with all beings anyone's -
mm-hmm it's the same framework yeah
obviously most often these things are
prompted in people by interacting with
other people but it's it's the same
animals pleasant animals unpleasant
animals want to feel you fear the ones
you hate the ones you like the one who
dislike same people so the mind of
friendliness means mind of non house you
won't have a friend yeah
friends trying to bite you you lose the
context thought that he is your friend
we're trying to think of regard to I
mean like how I've seen sometimes
compassion interpreter is like the
action for the reaction it's the
reaction yeah like oh you practice
compassion by spreading love by
spreading this by beaming it by
radiating it I've also seen I was like
wishing for that person yes I wish you
well well wishing is you met the
practice no actually well wishing sorry
Metta practice is understanding what the
nature of friendliness is what that
framework is and then cultivating
regardless of whether somebody's
upsetting your not that's what the
Buddha is a suited and he says the
Buddha said though he would he would go
sit down
establish his mindfulness to the mouse
and then enter John or he would come
back from venomous sit down establishing
monstermouth and the second server oh
he'll come back from the pinna but
instead she's masters in a month and
practice development for brahmacaris so
it's something you do when you're on
your own because if you if your mind is
developed in that framework that
everybody is your friend regardless of
directions inwards then when you do
encounter people they will be within
that framework
they will be friends and you don't need
to do anything you don't need to make
any effort towards them because that's
not what friendship is it's the attitude
of the mind with a friendship base
that's what I mean by framework yeah no
oh but I need what can I may my mother
of course you wish your mother to be
well may my friends be woman while you keep
may my friends be woman while you keep
repeating this mechanically understand
what take your friend take your mother
take people that you regard with
friendly eye and understand the nature
of friendliness regardless of the
content of the people that's why brown
avocados are loftier bodies could you
actually transcend the content of
engagement passion your will all of that
you do it right that you will abandon
sensuality as well mmm from the horrors
I will exclusively only I guess the
disciples of the noble ones you need to
have a right view for any type of mind
establishment but that doesn't mean you
shouldn't be trying to do hmm
so cuz I mean I'm thinking about in
regard to other ascetics Rajanna
oh I don't know I don't know I don't
think it was mentioned that much in
sutras in that sense but I would assume
there are probably people who cultivated
you know the compassion to the whole
world plants inanimate objects you know from
plants inanimate objects you know from
the ultimate point of view of ownership
it's kind of well it's not adequate yeah
but it's it's probably still quite a
decent mind development to not be able
to hate anything or anyone that's
already quite something
by having it having right view given I
think even Jesus might have been
teaching that in the nutshell so I think
you know people get some recognition of
it you had this other Indian sort of
holy man
of them often revolving around that non
harmfulness they are inks the principal
the joins but but yeah I think the way
the Buddha was teaching is more like
actually properly done in a sense of
properly established on the nature of
that thing and then you understand it
and then you don't need to be emulating
or or going through the motions of
expressing it
so to speak mm-hmm having using the
cultivation of progress in regard to
write you for uprooting conceit and
sensuality yeah well imagine now like
you go back to Cote and you look again
recall a friend something in your mind
but not the specific character or person
but just like try to ponder and discern
the signs and characteristics of that
friendship aspect the nature of the just
friendship in general how what is your
mind like when it's when it's
experiencing a phenomenon of
friendliness the more familiar you
become with a tremulous the more
established that phenomenon is
regardless of who you have to deal with
it will be seen through that phenomenon
and that's why you would be unable to
hate that not because you love them you
don't need to love them they said you
can just all you need to do is not get
into hate and eternal love is always I
mean how I always see is like if
something's taken away if that thing
that I love is taking theirs they're
gonna be sadness and I think it isn't
like almost like a semi intentional
effort to blur the line between love
which is an inevitable infatuation
attachment requirement lead and the
spiritual love which is clean of that
and pure of that that's impossible
mm-hm if it's love means you're
overshooting the mark if it's hate means
you're overshooting the mark you're not
seeing the middle of it
and the people think well the Buddha had
a love no he didn't he didn't even want
to teach he said it's a hassle who why
would I waste my time and huh eight out
of ten people won't understand what I'm
saying and when the supreme Brahman then
came in asking three times begged him to
do it because well at least to earth and
evil will understand him too that excuse
it's a great thing and then the world
decided okay he'll teach not because he
loved them but because he had compassion
in the same sense a doctor who knows the
cure to the illness of the humanity
humankind would decide to share his
medicine but he said himself like when
when the man asked him how do you get
related when when your disciples that
you know fulfill your teachings to get
sad when they don't and he said let me
ask in return somebody comes and ask you
for a way to certain village and you
tell him well at this Junction take left
and they that person takes right who you
are you upset on account Allah says no I
mean I've done my bit but he chose to go
the opposite way I said well so it's
with the talent I'd done my bit person
choose not to follow it
touch the plate this is pleasing in a
way like I wasted my time but that
displeasure does not overcome an
obsession so possess my mind then
somebody does what I suggest then what
is struggling to do then I'm pleased
because they followed my instructions
through and through and I didn't waste
my time talking to them but that
pleasure does not come over my mind and
obsess it and resist it as well so yeah
it's a compassion of yeah I can help you
and here is the cure here is the
medicine it is the diet it is a strict
set of rules here to adhere to and
follow what I say you don't do it how
could I possibly care about that not my
problem you do it okay good for you
there you go now you see for yourself
and that's it but people like again as I
said with these blurred lines between
our love and love because allows you to
indulge then this great compassion love
which is all revolves around you conceit
as well and all of the Buddha love to
all of us
certainly do know hmm never imagined the
one sort of where the Buddha says like
to the horse trainer like I kill them
like those that don't you know after
I've tried to train them and they still
don't listen to me woman yeah then I
killed him how by not talking to them
and that so I didn't finish with in
removing resentment also in regard to
you know ting ya know pay no attention
to yeah I've seen and then the following
suit it talks about there's a person
people of different bodily behavior
impure verbal behavior that is pure and
and regarding them as such you know with
this some whom have a plus eighty of
mind and how and which regard them I've
seen a certain portion of this would
quoted for in regard to compassion or
cultivated cultivating compassion mm-hmm
and I'll read that line now it says how
friends sure resentment be removed
toward a person whose bodily and verbal
behavior are impure and who does not
gain an opening of mine plus idea of
mine from time to time and as I suppose
a sick afflicted gravely ill person was
traveling along a highway in the last
village behind him in the next ahead of
him were both far away he would not
obtain suitable food and medicine or a
qualified attendant he would not get to
meet the leader of the village district
another man traveling more that highway
might see him and aroused sheer
compassion sympathy and tender concern
for him thinking Oh made this man obtain
suitable food suitable medicine and a
qualified attendant may he meet the
leader of the village and it may not
encounter calamity and disaster right
here and so - when a person bodily of
persons bodily and verbal behavior are
impure he does not gain from
time and opening of mine facility of
mine on that occasion one should arouse
sheer compassion but whose translation
is that bigger bodis right well that's
kind of satisfactory first time I not
see that it's for their welfare to be
restrained and develop their mind in
calmness and so on do you try to help
them so they can see that it's for their
own good
hmm but that's all you can do with
that's why even the Buddha said even in
his you know he's the Buddha himself the
supreme Buddha himself enlightening in
every way he said all I can do is point
the direction yeah I've just seen I've
seen this particular part of it this
should quote it sometimes in regard to
like the well wishing well that's a
thing see like yeah you'd in order for
you to do the well wishing you have to
forget and ignore and be unaware and non
discerning or the fact that you're
already compassionate most people
already have a recognition of what
compassion and helpfulness and
friendliness is hmm but practicing that
it's more like discerning the nature of
those phenomena not like emulating now
this whole new artificial method of
compassion on top of it so you can
somehow reconnect with it you're doing
it instead of it means the more you
commit to this ridiculous method of how
are you feeling now I'm so concerned
about you you will be covering up the
natural compassion which won't just
saying things that are compassionate but
will actually have a compassionate
perspective and say things that are
helpful they might not necessarily make
that person feel better that's again
when the doctor tells you what the
medicine is he might not be a pleasant
thing to him oh this is the treatment
but it's factually for your own good
but if a doctor just Pat's you
back hugs you cries with you full of
loving-kindness doesn't want to upset
you you know it's not real it's not real
good isn't it mm-hmm
you Dario because treatment is too
unpleasant to admit and that's that with
exploited people ever actually make the
effort to study the suitors hmm they
would see that the Buddha was sometimes
extremely extremely harsh in his verbal
telling off to the monks they were not
trying to see we're getting careless and
not like idiot monks but monks they
didn't know what they were doing but you
know like monks they were already
established in dumb I'm dying on it
there's a kind of somebody full of love
speak like this and you don't even need
me petals upsets someone who needs it
don't even go and read we Bunga stories
but the monks broke the rules how Buddha
then spoke to them mm-hmm so that's what
I mean like it's it's nothing to do with
its mommy in love and spreading my joy
to you it's more like out of my
friendliness I can't help you and that's
why I'm not sacrificing my own
perspective which is you are not aware
so it seemed like the other man knows
that there is the end of his suffering
he continues walking to the next village
he will get the proper care the man who
is stuck in between he doesn't know that
and he doesn't know that this man knows
that so yeah it may be sound arrogant to
him that this man is telling him where
to go but if he makes the effort he'll
confirm for himself and it's like this
is pure compassion pure non arrogance
because he didn't have to say that to me
it's nothing to him he doesn't know me
doesn't love me you know doesn't even
know that want to like spend time with
me so to speak yeah if he's so helpful
so this will mean compassion and all
these things even John is by the way are
developed by undoing everything that
blocks them in your experience and one
of the main reason one of the main thing
that God's them is the idea of a method
and performance and set of prescriptions
so this is
do this I do this I do it because even
like in the umbrella we hard as you know
people try to emulate and do it
mechanically in the spreading of metal
as you can spread your friendliness here
isn't here yeah but how would you then
spread Oh pecker
how can you spread how can you beam and
spread rays often difference how does
that work
so you're beaming indifference here's my
difference there it's the framework in
your mind if your mind is developed to
the point of imperturbable equanimity
fan no not nothing matters anymore
nothing can prepare their mind because
it's seen in the right order
hmm I seen it too I guess people are
teachers prescribing like this like you
know yeah hope you feel and if you hate
you need to get rid of it cause people
are so much dependent in their lay life
generally even monks actually on having
something to do if I have nothing to do
well it's not going mad hmm
so then even but they take on practice
so Tommy just becomes a new thing which
is something to do which is my cutie
mark like this my method man might
meditation technique and all that and he
you become dependent on having to do it
so if you come across instruction where
it is well you can't do it we can only
understand it which is not on the level
of doing well that's just for many
people that's hard to accept because
that means they need to undo their
compulsive dependence upon having
something to do and that's frightening
kid Adam it undermines you it
essentially which means you you will
have to feel that but those who are not
afraid to do it then they get to see the
direction where the mindfulness and
understanding and discernment and
everything as the world talks about is
so in regard to having to experience
being around a difficult person and then
hatred or resentment arising in regard
to them instead of standing there you
know in your mind wishing radiator you
don't you can't and you shouldn't try to
get rid of that resentment in a sense of
this should not be arising because it's
already there you don't want it
obviously yet it's there so you're now
trying to go against it while it's there
is just confirming its presence even
more instead you want to include it in
the right context context that you would
have had to have understood beforehand
and developed you can't include it
magically in the right context or set to
prescribe motions and mechanical methods
because that's not what the context is
so you won't understand the context that
can include presented context of
friendship you can be upset with your
friend because he's saying something or
he's acting inappropriately whatever
that's upset but you still don't
question a friendship and to that extent
you're still not losing perspective on
your behavior means even if your friend
is acting like an idiot you're not going
to get upset and dismiss him you try and
help him because he's still primarily
within the framework of friendship yeah
if you really pushes it then you might
dismiss the whole framework but in this
case you want to not dismiss the
framework in regard to people whom you
don't even know because you can still
maintain the framework of friendliness
people animals you don't even need
engagement on the level of personalities
so anything opposite of me is within the
framework of friendliness that I
cultivate so if I experience resentment
each within the framework of the or the
friendliness I cultivate us it's not
really the resentment that you would
like that and then it will cease as a
resentment it's going to be just a
responsive no this is a genuinely
foolish behavior that is disagreeable so
then the resentment is just seen as a
disagreeable counterpart of that
behavior but it's not taken personally
and it's certainly not rooted in your
anger or
we'll anymore because that's what we
would save and sometimes if they if they
you know if you get like paired with a
fool it's factually his behavior is
foolish she's a foolish man you leave
but people like think is is this
non-discriminating all-encompassing
universal love towards everything I just
love everything mmm I'm in love with
everything which means I'm oblivious to
the nature of action of that person I
don't see how they behave because I just
love everyone I don't care yeah no you
do care you're just trying to override
it and pretend it's not there is is
there a way of them if you see that
you've lost the contest and you say oh I
should not say anything I should not do
anything I should walk away yeah that is
the if if you if you have lost the
context and you're certain that you
cannot act out of the right perspective
didn't yeah you restrain it strain
yourself walk away or said ignore until
it subsides because you obviously
haven't developed there the framework
you know sufficiently enough I've seen
people saying that would be your act of
compassion or friendliness because you
did not engage at all
yeah that's true that's true because
it's like you know you have hatred on
one side and non hatred on the other
side you have acts of hatred on one side
and add some non hatred on the other
side so to that extent you're
contributing to the betterment of that
situation so yeah if it comes like well
you walk away you can't act out of hate
been so to that extent you prevented
half of the hate that would have been in
that situation then we didn't escalate
in the opposing end of the other head
deal with an arrest review and that's
what Hayden bit more hate